{
  "reference_number": "12512",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a 2050 target in legislation now",
      "answer_index": 0,
      "notes": "At the least, the Government should set a 2050 target in legislation now. Taking into account the dramatic and dangerous impacts of\n climate change already on our doorstep, legislation should establish the goal of limiting warming to 1.5 degrees, and that means\n\n rapid cuts in all greenhouse gases beginning now. I support a net-zero target of 2040 with the majority of cuts occurring over the\n next decade."
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Emissions - Net zero emissions across all greenhouse gases by 2050",
      "answer_index": 1,
      "notes": "Methane needs to be treated the same as carbon because of the intensity of its warming effect. Considering our emissions are\n\n disproportionately made up of methane, compared to other countries, we need to set a global precedent for the treatment of\n methane."
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including from new forest planting)",
      "answer_index": 7,
      "notes": "I believe New Zealand’s targets must be achieved by actual cuts in our own emissions, and not through the purchase of overseas\n carbon credits or an over-reliance on forests as carbon sinks. I support mitigation steps that benefits the communities in which they\n\n are situated, and enable local people to enact the structural change we need for a safe climate future."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "I only support this clause if it is to revise the target to be more ambitious."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "Yes - the third emissions budget should be able to be changed but only when the subsequent budget is set",
      "answer_index": 4,
      "notes": "There should only be allowance to alter the last emissions budget if it is to increase ambition and scope of action. There should be\n no allowance for an incoming government to weaken action/budget."
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Under exceptional circumstances, yes. For example, it might be appropriate to change an upcoming budget after an extreme natural\n\ndisaster (such as a major earthquake). Any revision should require input from the Climate Change Commission and approval by\nParliament."
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "I support the focus on scientific knowledge, social circumstances and the Treaty of Waitangi taking precedence in considerations for\nbudgets. I also encourage global and local leadership, and creating a just and inclusive society to be included as key considerations.\n\nEconomic consideration is important, but needs to be considered in a long-term manner, that highlights the cost of inaction, and that\ntaking action early reduces the economic burden on future generations."
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "This is a necessity."
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "I support the principles of climate justice and just transition by putting the responsibility for climate change with those most\nresponsible for causing it. The poor, low-wage workers, Indigenous, and women must be empowered and enabled by, not be laden\n\nwith the costs of, climate change mitigation and adaptation. The government should also consider our global footprint. Investment\nportfolios need to be accounted for in emission budgets. Investments in high emitting industries, such as the fossil fuel industry and\n\nintensive dairying, must be counted as our own emissions. It is unacceptable to fund and profit from these practices without taking\nresponsibility for mitigating emissions. In the same sense, we must be answerable to mitigating the emissions of our exported\nproducts, such as coal."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Advising the Government on policy settings in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 6,
      "notes": "The Climate Commission should only advise on ETS settings, it should not make final decisions"
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "The delegation of commissioners should prioritise women, Māori, Pasifika, and climate scientists."
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "There has been a distinct lack of leadership from central government on adaptation. Guidance and a national plan should be\n\ndeveloped with local government."
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "I support the Government being required to prepare a national climate risk assessment, and a national policy plan to address these\nrisks."
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Thank you.\n\n\n\n\n You have elected to withhold your personal details from publication."
    }
  ]
}
